<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="jahlborn@users.sf.net">James Ahlborn</author>
    <title>Builder style classes for creating SQL queries</title>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section name="SqlBuilder">
      <p>
        SqlBuilder is a library which attempts to take the pain out of
        generating SQL queries within Java programs.  Using one programming
        language (Java) to generate code for another language (i.e. SQL) is
        always a challenge.  There are always issues with escaping characters
        within string literals, getting spaces in the right place, and getting
        the parentheses to match up.  And often, even after the code is
        debugged and fully tested, it is still very fragile.  The slightest
        change will throw things out of balance and require another round of
        testing and tweaking.
      </p>
      <p>
        SqlBuilder changes that whole scenario by wrapping the SQL syntax
        within very lightweight and easy to use Java objects which follow the
        "builder" paradigm (similar to StringBuilder).  <i>This changes many
        common SQL syntactical, runtime errors into Java compile-time
        errors!</i>  Let's dive right in to some quick examples to to see how
        it all works.
      </p>
      <subsection name="SelectQuery Example">
        <p>
          A fairly simple SQL select query embedded in a Java program
          might currently look something like this:
        </p>
        <source>
// assuming a variety of predefined string constants
String selectQuery = "SELECT " + T1_COL1 + "," + T1_COL2 + "," +
  T2_COL1 + " FROM " + TABLE1 + " " + T1 + " INNER JOIN " +
  TABLE2 + " " + T2 + " ON (" + T1_IDCOL + " = " + T2_IDCOL +
  ") ORDER BY " + T1_COL1;
</source>
        <p>
          Whenever this query is modified, you will need to make sure there
          are sufficient commas, parentheses, and spaces to generate the
          correct query (not to mention the correct columns for the given
          tables and the correct aliases for those tables).
        </p>
        <p>
          An attempted improvement may look something like this:
        </p>
        <source>
String selectQuery = MessageFormat.format(
  "SELECT {0},{1},{2} FROM {3} {4} INNER JOIN {5} {6} ON ({7} = {8}) " +
  "ORDER BY {9}",
  T1_COL1, T2_COL2, T2_COL1, TABLE1, T1, TABLE2, T2,
  T1_IDCOL, T2_IDCOL, T1_COL1);
</source>
        <p>
          This technique at least removes some of the formatting issues, as
          the query syntax is in one contiguous string.  However, matching up
          the placeholders with the arguments is no simple task and simple
          rearrangements can easily mess up the resulting query string.
          Additionally, this is still not a viable solution for any sort of
          dynamic query generation.
        </p>
        <p>
          Now, let's see how this query looks using SqlBuilder classes:
        </p>
        <source>
// assuming these objects have already been created
Table table1, table2;
Column t1Col1, t1Col2, t2Col1;
Join joinOfT1AndT2;

String selectQuery =
  (new SelectQuery())
  .addColumns(t1Col1, t1Col2, t2Col1)
  .addJoin(SelectQuery.JoinType.INNER_JOIN, joinOfT1AndT2)
  .addOrderings(t1Col1)
  .validate().toString();
</source>
        <p>
          See how easy that was?  Not a single embedded comma, space, or
          parenthesis to be seen!  Notice how much more readable this version
          is compared to the previous versions?  While the Java is a bit more
          verbose, turning the SQL into Java allows you to utilize your
          existing Java toolset when writing SQL (think compile-time syntax
          checking and IDE code completion).  This added functionality is well
          worth the trade-off.
        </p>
        <p>
          On top of that, check out the <code>validate()</code> method call
          slipped into the end of the statement.  That call will verify that
          the columns and tables in the query actually make sense.
          Maintainability, readability, and verifiability all wrapped into one
          easy to use package.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection>
        <p>
          That was a very simple example of course.  Imagine a much more
          complicated query with multiple sub-expressions in the where clause,
          and it should be easy to see the power and utility of the SqlBuilder
          library.
        </p>
        <p>
          As a final note--for all that the SqlBuilder package is, there are a
          couple of things it is <em>not</em>.  This package will <em>not</em>
          help you write SQL if you do not already know how to write SQL and
          use JDBC.  It does not abstract away the knowledge necessary to deal
          with a database, but instead provides tools for avoiding the more
          error-prone parts of generating SQL queries.  If you want a tool to
          completely abstract away the database, check out
          <a href="http://www.hibernate.org">Hibernate</a> instead.  There is
          a time and place for straight SQL and a time and place for an ORM
          tool.  If you are currently in the former time and place, then
          SqlBuilder is a tool you should definitely check out.
        </p>
      </subsection>
    </section>
    <section name="Getting Started">
      <ul>
        <li><a href="example.html">Basic examples</a></li>
        <li>Additional code examples in the <a href="apidocs/overview-summary.html#overview_description">sqlbuilder overview javadocs</a></li>
        <li>Major highlights of the supported syntax in the <a href="syntax_reference.html">Syntax Reference</a></li>
        <li>Examples for all the classes in the <a href="xref-test/com/healthmarketscience/sqlbuilder/SqlBuilderTest.html">unit tests</a></li>
        <li><a href="apidocs/index.html">Javadoc API documentation</a></li>
        <li><a href="xref/index.html">Complete source code (with cross references)</a></li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section name="Features">
      <ul>
        <li>Good portion of commonly used SQL (see the <a href="apidocs/com/healthmarketscience/sqlbuilder/package-summary.html#package_description">package summary</a> for a
            more complete list), including:
        <ul>
          <li><code>SELECT, UPDATE, DELETE, INSERT, CREATE, DROP,
              UNION</code></li>
          <li>Most boolean logic</li>
          <li>Most numeric expressions</li>
        </ul>
        </li>
        <li>99% of the SqlBuilder codebase is ANSI SQL92 compliant</li>
        <li>JDBC escape syntax support (<a href="apidocs/com/healthmarketscience/sqlbuilder/JdbcEscape.html">JdbcEscape</a>)</li>
        <li>Helpers for managing PreparedStatement parameters (<a href="apidocs/com/healthmarketscience/sqlbuilder/QueryPreparer.html">QueryPreparer</a>) and reading results (<a href="apidocs/com/healthmarketscience/sqlbuilder/QueryReader.html">QueryReader</a>)</li>
        <li>Optional <a href="apidocs/com/healthmarketscience/sqlbuilder/Query.html#validate()">query validation</a></li>
        <li>Two usage modes:
        <ul>
          <li>Predefined, strongly verifiable <a href="apidocs/com/healthmarketscience/sqlbuilder/dbspec/package-summary.html">database model</a> (optionally using the included <a href="apidocs/com/healthmarketscience/sqlbuilder/dbspec/basic/package-summary.html">basic implementation</a>)</li>
          <li>Fully customized, weakly verifiable constants using <a href="apidocs/com/healthmarketscience/sqlbuilder/CustomSql.html">CustomSql</a></li>
        </ul>
        </li>
        <li>Does <i>not</i> do any form of SQL string escaping:
        <ul>
          <li>SQL escapes are database dependent</li>
          <li>SQL escaping is pretty much impossible to do correctly in a
              library external to the database</li>
          <li>PreparedStatements should always be used to avoid any need for
              string escaping (use <a href="apidocs/com/healthmarketscience/sqlbuilder/QueryPreparer.html">QueryPreparer</a> for a convenient helper)</li>
        </ul>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
